我不在乎瓦里留斯摸过你
I did not care for Varinius' hand upon you.
我也是
Nor I.
那个姑娘 妮维雅
The girl, Naevia.
他说了什么
What did he say?
她死了
Dead.
那奴隶贩子没说妮维雅已死
The slaver told not of her death,
说的是她在矿区受苦受难
but of her suffering in the mines!
我站在克雷斯这边 一定要救出妮维雅
I stand with Crixus. And will see Naevia from bondage.
我要去维苏威
I move for Vesuvius.
想活命的 跟我走
Those that would live, join me.
尊贵的瓦里留斯
Noble Varinius!
我向你们致歉
I offer apologies.
我的士兵们前去追寻更崇高的目标
My soldiers have been set to higher purpose!
进矿坑 快
Into the mines, quickly!
此时此刻
At this very moment,
他们已逼近斯巴达克斯
they close on Spartacus!
你没事了 现在安全了
You're safe, you're safe now.
克雷斯
Crixus?
带妮维雅到安全的地方
Take Naevia to a safe place!
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《徒劳》
妮维雅
Naevia!
站住
Halt!
从左面包抄
Swing around to the left!
我去追她
I got her!
你害我好一顿跑
You made me run.
我最他妈讨厌跑路了
I fucking hate running.
我要把泰科斯埋了
I would see Tychos to ground.
不能落到罗马人手里
Far from Roman hands.
追兵来了
More come.
好吧
Right!
我们没时间了
There is no time for it.
无关紧要
It does not fucking matter.
反正我们就快跟他见面了
We shall all join him soon.
抓住斯巴达克斯
Spartacus shall fall.
这不正是我来卡普亚的原因吗
Is that not the reason for my presence in Capua?
狗屁的原因
To shit with reason.
你的军队缺席比赛
The absence of your troops from the games
是对瓦里留斯的大不敬
was an insult to good Varinius.
如果我背离了初衷
The Republic would bear far greater slight,
是对共和国的大不敬
were I to turn from purpose.
赛普修斯搜寻色雷斯人数月之久
Seppius has been searching for the Thracian for months.
你凭什么预言他会攻击卢卡尼亚的矿区
How came you to divine he would make attempt on the mines at Lucania?
因为这是诸神的意思
Because the gods themselves presented it,
由他们的使者传达给我
through voice of humble servant.
露迪雅
Lucretia?
我的行动是听了她的建议
Her counsel moved my hand.
这么说倒是有道理
Perhaps your course was justified then.
但愿是真的
I pray it true.
否则就因为一个疯女人的胡话冒犯了贵人
Otherwise offense has been made upon the ramblings of a madwoman.
这件事都过去了 伊莉西娅
We have moved past this, Ilithyia.
精神上算是吧
In spirit, at least.
那就来点实在的 举办一场宴会
Let us make it a thing of the flesh, with celebration.
就在这里 算是补偿你了
Here within these walls, to pay tribute owed.
好主意
An excellent notion!
你接受吧
Well received, yes?
我要是拒绝就是自讨没趣了
It would stand the more grievous insult to refuse.
我很荣幸
You honor me.
这是我的荣幸
The honor is mine.
我只想帮忙
I only thought to help.
在我们家举办宴会
By plying that preening shit
讨好那个自大的混蛋也算帮忙
with celebration in our own house?
我们家在罗马 盖尤斯
Our house is in Rome, Gaius.
我想要尽快回去
And I would speed return.
有瓦里留斯支持 你就能使唤赛普修斯的人
With Varinius' support, you will have Seppius' men.
如今用不着那帮家伙了
Now worth their weight in piss.
按照露迪雅所言 马科斯抓回斯巴达克斯
When Marcus returns to us with Spartacus as Lucretia
你太抬举她了
You place too high a value on her.
一旦失败 她就害惨我们了
She will drag us to ruin when it plummets.
露迪雅不断地证明
Lucretia continues to prove herself
她值得这样的抬举
worthy of such estimation.
希望我的妻子也能一样
Would that my own wife held the same.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
她需要休息
She needs a moment.
她需要赶紧上路
She needs to fucking move.
如果你长年累月在矿上劳作
How quickly would your feet carry,
你这两条腿能跑多快
after months condemned to that place?
不只是她需要休息
She is not alone in needing rest.
体力不支 我们都撑不下去
The lack of it sets nerve to edge.
我们找一块高地
We will find higher ground,
打起来更好防守
better defended if set upon.
你能再坚持一会儿吗
Can you walk but a little more?
她能行的
She will make it.
走吧
Come on.
带着她 我们的担子越来越沉
The weight of her increases with each step.
也许是该卸下包袱
Perhaps it is time to lighten burden.
我答应过克雷斯
I swore a promise to Crixus.
她是那家伙的心肝
She is the man's heart.
你还要让他再撕心裂肺一次吗
Would you again tear it from his chest?
克雷斯死了
Crixus is dead.
我不要再管他的女人
And I would be free of his woman,
免得我们落到同样的下场
before we fucking share the same fate.
我们去维苏威找艾力冈
We move for Vesuvius, to rejoin Agron.
大家都去
All of us.
再说这种话
Speak of this again
休怪我无情无义
and the Romans will be the least of your concerns.
泰科斯
Tychos.
小角色一个
One of the lesser men.
当作给他们的警告
Let him serve as a warning.
让他们知道反抗罗马的下场
That Rome is not so easily defied.
他们的人数减少了
Their numbers dwindle.
可我们的人手也在锐减
Yet ours follow at more rapid pace.
我们还是占优势
We still hold the greater sum.
斯巴达克斯他们都是角斗士
Spartacus and his men are gladiators.
你们这么点人根本不可能对抗一个…
A handful of your men would stand pale shadow against one
罗马士兵知道死亡是怎么回事
Roman soldiers know something of death,
知道死亡的代价
and the dealing of it.
不要拿他们和普通奴隶相提并论
Do not measure their worth against common slaves.
奴隶倒不假
Slaves, true.
可绝对不普通
But far from common.
调来其余的正规军
Move absent proper force...
确保我们能除掉狠角色
and see the rank of the dead swell.
你们在树林中的战线拉得太长了
Your men are spread too thin throughout the forest.
只用派一个人轻装回程
A single man carried by swift purpose
就能带回大批的援军
could return with reinforcements...
通知各个分队
Carry word to the other squads.
不许休息
We do not rest.
护民官
Tribune
搜查到底
See this to its end
以盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博之名
in the name of Gaius Claudius Glaber.
你要是敢跑
Turn from your charge,
我他妈的保证一刀捅了你
and I'll put a sword in your fucking back.
瓦里留斯是最尊贵的客人
Varinius is a man of the highest regard.
他的酒杯不能空
See his cup always full
满足他的一切需求
and all desires met.
听懂了吗
Am I understood?
- 听懂了 - 是 主人
- Domina. - Yes, Domina.
你们先去洗漱和准备
Bathe and prepare yourselves.
赛皮娅
Seppia.
抱歉 没人告诉我你来了
Apologies, I was not told of your arrival.
没必要
None required.
我来听取露迪雅的建议
I came seeking Lucretia's counsel.
似乎很多人都喜欢来找她呢
A thing desired by many it would seem.
你的话给她指明了道路
Your words set her to path.
我的话
Mine?
你一直在赞美婚姻的好处
You are forever extolling the virtues of marriage.
多年积累的智慧让我这样的小年轻不服不行
Wisdom of years has finally proven master over fatuous youth.
这么快你就找到丈夫了吗
You've found a husband so quickly?
如果诸神保佑的话
If the gods bless such a union.
我会为你向诸神祈祷的
I shall entreat them on your behalf.
有诸神保佑 瓦里留斯肯定属于你
With their favor, Varinius shall be yours.
瓦里留斯
Varinius?
他很英俊吧
Is he not handsome?
又高又壮 还有钱
And tall and strong and of means?
他是那种所有女人都渴望得到的男人
The form of a man every woman longs to call her own!
他能成为无人可比的好丈夫
He would make a husband to rival all others.
我要去为出席宴会做准备了
I must prepare myself for his celebration.
我要吸引他的注意
I would catch his eye,
然后占据他的全部身心
and with it see the rest of him swiftly follow.
她这样是受你的影响
You have made impression upon her.
还有你的吧
As have you.
人们不用千里迢迢去特尔斐朝圣了
No longer is pilgrimage needed to Delphi.
要得到诸神的指引
Those seeking the consideration
只需要向卡普亚的圣人顶礼膜拜
of the gods need only bow to the Oracle of Capua.
我只是诸神的工具
I am but humble vessel,
给他们的愿望添点儿滋味
offering a mere taste of their will.
那赛皮娅今晚尝到的会是苦味吧
Then Seppia shall find tonight a bitter draught.
瓦里留斯是民政官
Varinius is a praetor.
你丈夫也是民政官
As is your husband.
但是瓦里留斯爬得更快
Yet Varinius rises more quickly,
终有一天 他会成为执政官
and one day shall hold title of consul.
这种人的妻子必须温文尔雅 处事冷静
The wife of such a man must possess refinement and poise.
乳臭未干的小姑娘根本做不到
Traits yet lacking in a spoiled little girl.
你是要我祈求诸神 另谋姻缘
Perhaps you would have me petition the gods for a different union?
更合心意的…
One closer to heart...
谁有这种奢望 那是癞蛤蟆想吃天鹅肉
The morning cock has better chance of crowing to such heights.
你丈夫并不这样认为
Your husband believes otherwise.
你父亲也是
As does your father.
如果马科斯没抓回斯巴达克斯
When Marcus returns absent Spartacus,
你的真面目就暴露出来了
you shall be revealed as what you are.
没有生命 不能预言的工具
An empty vessel, barren of life and prophecy.
穿好衣服准备参加宴会吧
See yourself dressed for tonight.
毫无疑问 我夫君要把你当做爱宠拿去炫耀
I have no doubt my husband will wish to parade you about as favored pet.
我很珍惜你丈夫对我的信任
Your husband's trust is valued gift.
我更珍惜你对我的信任
Yet yours would prove the greater treasure.
列队
Line them up.
我没有辜负你们的信任
The faith placed in me is not mislaid.
斯巴达克斯确实在我预言的地方
Spartacus proves where I predicted.
民政官
Praetor.
这就是你们抓住的人吗
This is all that stand captured?
还有很多死在矿坑里了
Many more lay dead in the mines.
至少你的高卢人回来了
Your Gaul returns to you at least.
斯巴达克斯在哪儿
Where is Spartacus?
他带着几个奴隶逃进树林里了
He fled into the woods with a clutch of slaves.
马科斯去追了
Marcus gives chase.
看到他出现就立刻向我报告
Alert me the moment he is sighted upon road.
关进牢里
To the cells.
走
Move!
即使有你神圣的指引
Even aided by your divine guidance,
他还是两手空空
he stands with empty hands.
他会找到斯巴达克斯的
He will yet find Spartacus between them.
诸神…
The gods
你所说的根本不是诸神的旨意
Your tongue writhes absent their purpose.
妮维雅不是在我所预言的矿区吗
Was Naevia not found in the mines, as I foretold?
是谁把她赶到那里去的呢
And who so condemned her to such a place?
朱诺吗
Juno?
还是世俗的凡人 角斗士训练师的妻子
Or a Lanista's wife, more earthly bound?
你的预言不过是投机取巧的把戏
Your prophecies bear the stench of opportunity.
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus
是你亡夫的手下送来的
was delivered by your dead husband's man.
那家伙打伤人套出实情
A toad who has seen his share of wounds.
没准他还能治好伤
I wonder if he could mend them as well...
别以为我跟我丈夫和父亲一样傻
Do not think me the fool, as my husband and father.
咱们俩还有账没算完呢
You and I have unfinished affairs.
总有一天我们要做个了断
And I would see them draw to a close.
进去
Get in!
又回到臭茅坑家族了
Again to this House of Piss and Shit.
你们不该跟着我受苦
A fate I alone should bear.
我们知道有这样的危险
The risk was known to us all.
去他妈的危险 去他妈的混账罗马人
Fuck risk and fuck the fucking Romans.
我这辈子跟你混 下辈子也是
I stand with you, in this life and the next.
我也是
As do I.
这就是兄弟之情
The bonds of brotherhood.
在高墙之内根深蒂固地存在着
They have always run deep within these walls.
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus!
发生什么事了
What has happened?
你怎么在这儿
How did you come here?
我做了傻事
I was a fool.
不过现在有傻子来陪我了
That now stands in fellow company.
他们错在跟着我踏上不归路
Their fault lies only in following me on impossible journey.
妮维雅还活着
Naevia lives.
我们把她从矿区救出来了
We liberated her from the mines.
爱情
Love.
你因为爱情而毁灭
You fall to ruin for love.
她是我的全部
She is my heart.
她只是个女人
She is a woman.
再怎么说也就是脆弱的生物
A delicate creature at the best of times.
她们容易受到欲望的驱使
They are moved by desires unknown
男人一无所知 却还那么信任她们
by the men that place trust in them.
她还活着
She lives.
这才是最重要的
That is all that matters.
你没事了
You are safe now.
安全了
You are safe.
不去休息吗
You do not rest?
我不想再看到有人丧命
I would not see another of us fall.
就算诸神下凡 也未必阻止得了
Not even the gods could have done more to prevent it.
这想法可不能让逝者安息
A thought holding no comfort to the dead.
妮维雅
Naevia.
李斯卡斯
Liscus!
纳西尔
Nasir!
他不顾一切地救我
He risked life, to save my own.
真是大饱眼福啊
A most impressive showing!
难以想象前些日子这里跟坟墓没两样
It staggers to think this house so recently a tomb.
这间宅子完全没有血腥恐怖的痕迹了
These walls truly present no evidence of witnessed horrors.
这些不快的记忆很快便会烟消云散
Such memories shall soon be cleansed from thought,
不会再来影响你的心情
never again to darken mind.
我渴盼已久了
I long for such a day.
那我们纵情饮酒 尽情享乐吧
Let us hasten it with ample libation.
恐怕一杯酒见底 蒙卡图就要不省人事
I fear Mercato may lose himself in the bottom of a cup,
忘记自个儿的身份地位了
and forget that we are of position.
我绝不会出此洋相
I would never make spectacle of myself.
那么来吧
Come then!
我倒要试试你的酒量
I would test the strength of your resolve.
还有我的
And my own as well!
我从没见过加里恩努斯兴致如此高涨
I have never beheld sour Gallienus in such high spirits.
看来这场宴会的确是明智之举
This celebration already proves clever suggestion.
如有斯巴达克斯被捕的消息 那就更好了
To be made brilliant, if Spartacus' capture were to be announced.
有诸神庇佑 今晚可能有意外的惊喜
The gods may yet bless us this night with unexpected gifts.
那就用美酒与欢歌向诸神祈祷
Let us entreat them with wine and song!
让我们的声音传至奥林匹斯山
Our voices to carry to Olympus itself!
这间宅子以前距离奥林匹斯很近呢
This house once sat perched within its reach.
有时候我亲自到此朝拜
I have worshipped here myself upon occasion.
科萨特斯
Good Cossutius.
你竟然也到卡普亚来了
I had not heard you were in Capua.
他来看我的角斗比赛
He comes for my games.
顺便离开罗马 避开某人的监视
And to remove himself from the prudish eyes of Rome.
合情合理
Both just cause.
来吧
Come.
共同欣赏吧
Let us enjoy spectacle.
果真是感官盛宴啊
Truly a feast for the senses.
我都无法用言语表达了
Even I stand speechless.
那我该抓住这难得的时机
Then I shall seize upon rare moment,
礼敬各位贵客
to honor noble guest.
卡普亚的子民们
Good citizens of Capua!
前来这间曾受到诅咒的宅子
Your presence here in this house once stood cursed
证实了你们的勇气和信念
is testament to your courage and faith.
不仅是对我的信念
Faith not only in me,
更是对元老院的信念
in the body of the Senate as well.
元老院代表 敬爱的阿比努斯
Represented by beloved Albinius
和尊贵的瓦里留斯
and noble Varinius.
我们应该举办宴会答谢他的慷慨之举
A man worthy of celebration for his generosity
他用角斗比赛消遣民众
in providing distraction with games
消除大家的忧虑
to ease troubled thoughts!
瞧瞧 他们多么拥戴你
See how they admire you.
这女孩当真遵从了你的建议
The girl takes your counsel to heart.
而我将以恶人遭报的好消息
And I repay your kind attendance
回敬各位的出席
with welcome news of retribution.
我的手下带来了
My soldiers return with news
斯巴达克斯即将被捕的消息
of Spartacus'imminent capture...
并提前献上
and offer in advance the lives
几个他最为信任的孽党残余
of the few surviving remnants of his most trusted men.
这些角斗士 这些奴隶
These gladiators... these slaves,
正是杀害诸位亲人的元凶
were responsible for the deaths of many of your noble kin.
他们将用
And they will pay...
血来偿还
with blood.
民政官瓦里留斯
Praetor Varinius.
因有要事 我的手下未能
Pressing concerns forced hand in preventing my men
出席您的角斗比赛
from presenting at your games.
为此我献上这几个罗马敌人的性命
I offer you the lives of these enemies of Rome,
为我的无意之举致歉
to balm unintentional wounds.
杀掉这些畜生
Cut the pig!
来啊 我们要见血
Come on, we want blood!
很感激有此荣幸
Gratitude for this honor.
感激你不辞辛劳 追捕恶棍斯巴达克斯
And for your tireless pursuit of the villain Spartacus.
然而我无法接受
Yet I cannot accept.
我不接受 是因为这么做
I cannot accept because to do so
会剥夺本城市民应该享受的快乐
would rob the people of this city of deserved pleasures.
不要让他们仅因一人的荣耀
Let these men not fall here tonight
今晚就倒在了这里
in the honor of a single man,
让他们去角斗场 当着整个卡普亚战死
but in the arena before all of Capua!
找到水了
Water!
快喝点
Drink.
这小伙子很勇猛
The boy fought well.
如果这是酒
Would this were wine,
就可以送他上路了
to send him properly on his way.
你说得好像他死了一样
You speak of him as if already gone.
他说的就是事实
Then he speaks the truth.
这问题我们谈过了
We have settled this.
理智一点
Come to reason.
他失掉了体内一大半的血
There is more blood upon the ground than yet within him.
就算我们带上他 他还是活不成
Even if we carry him, he will not survive.
反而留下血迹
But he will leave a trail.
罗马人跟着就能找到我们
One that the Romans shall follow.
我们不能把他丢下
We cannot just leave him.
对 确实不能
No. We cannot.
你想杀掉他
You would take his life?
我只是送他早点上路
I would but sever dangling thread.
这是对他好
It would be a kindness.
我不准你碰他
You will not touch him.
那你来杀他
Then do it yourself.
让他脱离苦海 就像你对维罗做的…
Put him from misery, as you did Varro
克雷斯
Crixus.
更重的伤他都活过来了
He survived worse.
就是对战瑟奥科斯的那次
Against Theokoles.
如果用火愈合伤口
The boy too will live.
这个男孩也能活命
If his wound is sealed with fire.
生火会招来罗马人
A fire would call the Romans down upon us.
那我们必须动作快
Then we must be quick,
在他们追来之前就逃走
and be gone before they arrive.
如果逃不了呢
And if we are not?
我们没有足够的人手
We do not have enough men.
没错 是没有
No. We do not.
你要找到艾力冈 把大家都带来
Find Agron and bring all to purpose.
我们会尽快跟过来
We will follow as swiftly as we are able.
恐怕你们没那么快
I fear it will not be swift enough.
虽说如同待宰的猎物
Trussed as game awaiting slaughter,
他们的眼神还很凶啊
yet the man still eyes us as prey.
很快他们眼睛里的火焰就会熄灭了
The fire will soon be put from rebellious eyes.
正好给你的角斗比赛收场 瓦里留斯
A fitting end to your games, Varinius.
绝对让人记忆深刻
It shall be a day etched in memory.
我等不及看到他们血溅沙场了
I cannot wait to see their blood spill upon the sands.
我也是
Nor I.
难道他们不该死在这里
Yet should they not fall here,
他们就在这里杀死了我们亲爱的堂兄塞克斯
in the very place they robbed our beloved cousin sextus of his life?
我们非常怀念他
A man dearly missed.
如果今晚不纪念他的话就太遗憾了
It is a pity he shall not be honored this night.
让他们死在整个卡普亚面前岂不是更有意义
Would the greater honor not be before all of Capua?
我们都是政客 对吧
We are politicians, are we not?
那我们各退一步吧
Let us come to middle ground,
这样大家都满意
and see everyone satisfied.
选一个人
Choose a single man,
然后拿他找找乐子 以此纪念你的堂兄
and let us make sport of him in memory of your cousin.
这真是再好不过了
A most judicious compromise!
可不止赛普修斯一人受到了伤害
Seppius is not the only one who stands injured.
诸神注意到了露迪雅所遭受的灾难
The gods themselves took note of the horrors inflicted upon Lucretia.
并且从往生世界救回了她的性命
And pluck her from the shores of the afterlife
以传达他们的旨意
to voice their desires.
这里原本是她的家族所在
Should she not choose what blood is shed
难道不应该由她决定谁生谁死吗
beneath roof she once claimed her own?
她承受的痛楚无人可比
She has been most sorely grieved.
如果没人反对的话
If there are no objections...?
谁有胆反对诸神的旨意呢
What mortal dares defy the gods?
反对的人只能引来诸神的怒火
Only one who would draw their wrath.
瓦里留斯刚刚决定
Varinius has seen fit to allow us
让我们见见叛贼的鲜血
a taste of the blood to come.
他们中的一个
A single man,
将被献祭给这间
to be sacrificed to this house
曾经被斯巴达克斯及其走狗
where so many lives were stolen
肆意屠戮的宅子
by Spartacus and his jackals.
由诸神通过他们的前主人
To be chosen by its former domina,
选出他们中的一人
the gods themselves guiding her hands.
诸神已经做出了决定
The gods have chosen.
就是他
This one.
我们应该抽签决定顺序
We shall draw lots,
并且不可致命 延长游戏的过程
and cut but shallow to prolong the game.
赛普修斯第一个来
Seppius to stand first,
以纪念他死去的堂兄
in honor of fallen cousin!
老子操死你们这些罗马猪
Fuck the lot of you Roman cunts!
不要以为诸神对你怀有仁慈之心
Do not think that the gods have shown you mercy.
我暂且饶你性命 是为了慢慢地享受
I but delay your passing, so that I may savor it.
我的命早就献给
My life is gladly given.
妮维雅了
For Naevia's.
她还活著
She lives?
你是别想找到她了
Far from your fucking grasp.
真是好消息啊
News greeted with joy.
我要把你临死的丑态告诉她
I would have her hear of your final moments.
你曾经那么热爱的竞技场
In the arena you held so dear.
那么多曾经为你疯狂的观众 是如何唾弃你
And the crowd which once cheered your name spitting upon you.
而当你倒下时 那可不是冠军的身份了
And when you fall, it will not be as champion.
只是一个普通奴隶
But as a common slave.
没有荣耀 没有尊严
Absent honor and absent glory
你的名字永远不会为人所铭记
and your name forever lost to history.
让他再说罗马人的坏话
Let this shit speak now of Romans!
第一滴血已经流下
First blood has been drawn!
下一个是谁
Who stands next?!
记住不要割得太深
Remember, do not cut too deep.
这样大家才能都享受到乐趣
I would not deprive everyone fair turn!
瓦里留斯刚来这里没多久
Varinius in town but a handful of days,
就掩盖了你夫君的光芒
and already outshines your husband.
他确实风度非凡
The man does exude presence.
胸部
The breast!
可你的心一直都向着盖尤斯
But your heart was always set upon Gaius.
我被这样的假象蒙蔽了好久
It is a deceitful thing that has led many astray.
不过年轻时的错误还是能改正过来的
Yet mistakes of youth need not forever haunt maturity.
你希望解除婚姻吗
You would see marriage dissolved?
我无权这样做
I do not hold such power.
只能由我最信任的父亲做决定
That decision lies in trusted father.
盖尤斯倒不是没犯过大错
Gaius is not without considerable fault.
不过这对我们家族的声誉有影响啊
Yet it would not lend favorably upon our name.
你怀着他的孩子呢
You carry his child,
而且他也身居民政官的高位
and he yet holds position of praetor.
又不只有他是民政官
He is not the only one with such title.
看来诸神青睐更年轻的人啊
It would seem the gods favor less mature schemes.
这种事情不要再想了 我也不会再想
Strike it from your thoughts, as I have from mine.
他快死了
He is fading.
找个东西让他咬着
Fetch something for him to clutch between teeth.
等我们做完
When it is done,
必须立刻灭火 离开这里
we must smother fire and move quickly.
我见过你这表情
I've seen that look.
还有你内心深处的自责
And the blame it inflicts inward.
他们不该承受这样的命运
None other deserve it.
这是我们的选择
We chose to do this.
即便是该死的李斯卡斯
Even fucking Liscus.
葛雷博不是派人来杀李斯卡斯的
Glaber does not send his men against Liscus.
是来杀我的
He sends them against me.
大家是因为我才遭此劫难
And all suffer because of it.
是
Yes.
因为你
It is because of you.
我们才能自由
That we are free.
你们干嘛呢
What are you doing?
我们要给你止血
We must close your wound.
那我就有烙印了
I am to be branded with fire.
跟真正的角斗士一样
As a true gladiator would.
你早就是我们的兄弟了
You have earned your place among the brotherhood.
按住他
Hold him down.
别喊出来
Do not cry out.
灭火 快
The fire! Quickly!
拿上剑 走
Take my sword! Go!
来 该你了
Come, it is your turn.
我还没拿过剑呢
I have never held one before.
我哥哥不允许
My brother would not allow it.
那就需要有经验的人教教你了
Well, then it falls to more experienced hands to guide you.
来
Come.
你不太喜欢主人找乐子
You do not care for your master's affections?
我没有主人
I am slave to no man.
但你对瓦里留斯可谓言听计从啊
Yet you bow and scrape toward Varinius' purpose.
只是帮我追捕斯巴达克斯
But aids me in pursuit of Spartacus.
这事儿我同样办得到
I would have done so as well.
而且不会搞你的妹妹
Absent attempt to fuck your sister.
行政官
Magistrate.
借一步说话
A word.
把剑尖对准皮肉
Now place the tip against flesh,
让你的欲望延伸到剑尖
and feel it part at your desire.
我
I...
我做不到
I cannot.
抱歉
Apologies
我们尊贵的客人对生手的要求太高了
Our honored guest asks too much of inexperienced hands.
您夫人杀人取命真是毫不手软
Your wife does not shy from taking life.
欲望就要这样满足
That is how you sate desire,
无论爱欲还是复仇
for love or vengeance.
都要毫不犹豫
Without hesitation.
风景很好 对吧
It is a sight, is it not?
俯瞰卡普亚全城
All of Capua laid at your feet.
我没兴趣看风景
It is not the view, but quiet respite
只想图个安静
from celebration that draws me.
那是我多嘴多舌 打扰您了
And I have shattered it with prattling tongue.
抱歉
Apologies.
回来
Linger.
这是你家的高枝 我岂能赶走女主人
I would not sweep you from perch once your own.
我好久没有这样形容这里了
It seems a lifetime ago I called it so.
光阴似箭啊
Time flees from us all.
徒留悲伤 日日夜夜地折磨我们
Leaving regret for what might have been churning in our wake.
恐怕我们是深有同感
I fear we share much in such regard.
丈夫死了
A husband lost.
妻子…
A wife...
切肤之痛
Dearly missed.
那就想想高兴的事儿吧
Let us turn to common joy,
朋友啊 女儿啊
of friend and daughter.
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia.
想到她 我也实在轻松不起来
The name fails to lighten troubled thoughts.
那就喊出来 把烦恼抛到九霄云外
Give them voice, and see them fly to the heavens.
我可没有喊出来的力气
I have not the lungs to shout so loud.
那就悄悄告诉我
Then whisper desire to me.
由我向诸神祈求 满足您的欲望
And I shall entreat the gods to see them satisfied.
你的提议着实令我感动
Your counsel would be much appreciated.
佛蒂斯呢
Where's Fortis?
我们躲开了一队罗马士兵
We avoided one squad of Romans.
结果又撞见一队
A second we could not.
逃跑的时候跟佛蒂斯失散了
I lost Fortis in the woods as we fled.
哪个方向
Which direction?
就是你们走的那边
The one which you travel in.
我们应该往西边走
We shall break to the west,
先甩掉他们再调整路线
and hope to miss them before righting course.
要是甩不掉呢
And if we do not?
那就让他们知道 受伤的野兽也不好欺负
Then they shall learn that a wounded animal may yet bare teeth.
你玩过火了
You overreach.
结果哭成了这样
And hot tears burn in result.
别理他了
Turn from him.
擦干眼泪
And dry your eyes.
我们离开这个狗屁地方
Let us leave this fucking house.
在温暖的怀抱里忘掉今晚的事
And see memory of this night fade in warm embrace.
是 哥哥
Yes, brother.
克拉苏 没错
Crassus, yes!
我经常跟他一起进餐 沐浴
Yes, I have dined and bathed with him upon many occasion.
那家伙银子多
A man large of coin...
鸡巴小
small of cock.
他的妻子倒是经常提起
His wife has often spoken of it.
赞不绝口呢
In far grander terms.
去喝点酒
Seek more wine.
我稍后就来
I shall join you presently.
你的口味是越来越年轻了呀
Your eye flits from young to younger still.
这样下去
If celebration stretches,
恐怕你会抱着女婴寻欢作乐了吧
I fear to discover you with a newborn clutched in hand.
伊莉西娅 我不希望
Ilithyia, I would not see my jest
克拉苏知道刚才的话
towards Crassus reach his ear.
那你怎么封住我的嘴呢
And what do you offer to purchase my silence?
你想要什么
What is it you seek?
讨好你的丈夫
Favor for your husband?
这些年我做的够多了
I have secured many for him over the years.
也该是时候
Perhaps it is time to place
考虑我自己的事了
myself higher in concern...
那是合情合理
It would be well deserved.
你为什么追求那种傻乎乎的小女孩
Why do you chase after simple little girls,
她们连胸部都没发育好
barely formed of breast?
她们没有牵绊嘛
They are unencumbered.
婚姻
Of marriage...
还有责任
and obligation...
如果有个女人配得上你 而且没有牵绊呢
And if a woman your equal stood removed from such?
我们这话是越说越明白了
We speak in ever tightening circles.
我希望能抓住要点
I would see them come to a point...
我父亲不喜欢盖尤斯
My father never favored Gaius.
如果有更加合适
If a more suitable husband
地位相等
with equal title
更有前途的人愿意做我的夫君…
and greater promise were to make his intentions known...
你玩的游戏很危险
You play a dangerous game.
值得冒险
With stakes worth the risk.
你的名字
Your name...
加上我父亲的
wed to my father's...
权力与财富
power and wealth
足以匹敌克拉苏
to rival Crassus himself...
先取得你父亲的同意解除婚约
Gain your father's approval to dissolve your marriage...
再带着你湿漉漉的身子来找我
and find me as wet with desire as you now stand.
操他妈的
Fuck the gods.
佛蒂斯
Fortis.
原路返回
Back the way we came.
李斯卡斯
Liscus!
我可是警告过你
Did I not fucking warn you?
伤太重了
A serious wound.
不过还能保命…
But you should live if
召集其余的小队
Call the remaining squad.
没有意义
It will not make a difference.
斯巴达克斯有诸神护体…
Spartacus is possessed by the gods themselves
斯巴达克斯就在这里
Spartacus is here!
给我上
Bear arms!
你会把他们招来的
You will draw them to us!
我们罗马战士要拼到最后一滴血…
And we will fight until the last drop of Roman blood
我不是罗马人
I am not a Roman.
我可不想今晚就死
And I will not fucking die this night.
我们要赶紧走 免得大军追来
We must move before more come.
我跑不动了
I am done running.
不要让兄弟们的血白流了
Do not fucking let this be for nothing.
活下去
Live...
送更多的罗马人去西天
and see many Romans fall...
你以为这样就能保命吗
You really believe this will save you?
主动爬上我父亲的床
Maneuvering my father's cock inside you?
你想错了
You mistake intent
不要再花言巧语了
Do not attempt to twist fucking word to advantage.
我再也不会跟着你的屁股走
I will not be placed beneath your heel again,
你个烂逼
you withered cunt.
你这么瞧不起我
You think so low of me?
那些满是鲜血和背叛的记忆 我可忘不掉
Based upon lasting memory of blood and betrayal.
我做过很多伤害你的事情
I've done many things to hurt you.
因为我嫉妒你
Because I was jealous.
你的地位 你的美貌
Of your position and your beauty.
你的年轻
Your youth.
我纯粹是下意识地做那些事
Moved by base passions which served only
结果伤了我自己的心
to wound my own heart.
我愿意做任何事 伊莉西娅
I would do anything, Ilithyia.
弥补过去所造成的伤害
To erase injury my actions have caused.
你想起来我们之间的事情了
You remember what happened between us?
我全都想起来了
I remember everything.
不要以为这么容易就能威胁到我
Do not think I will be so easily threatened.
你又想错了
Again, you mistake intent
错在你
Mistake is yours.
我要拿你的脑袋往石头上撞
I will dash your head against the stones
- 就像我对莱姬尼娅那样 - 等等
- as I did Licinia... - Wait!
就说你是失去理智攻击我
With tales of how you lost wits and came to me.
你父亲…
Your father
他不会为一个婊子的死而难过
Will not mourn the passing of a faded whore.
他愿意解除你的婚约
He will dissolve your marriage!
我就是为了这事才向他张开双腿
That is the reason I took him to my thighs.
说服他把你嫁给瓦里留斯
To sway him to your cause of wedding Varinius.
你不是这样希望的吗
That is what you desire, is it not?
就算是的 可我父亲凭什么
Even if it were, why would my father
听信你的花言巧语
be moved by serpent's tongue?
那是诸神在说话
The gods speak through me.
他认为诸神的建议充满智慧
He sees wisdom in their counsel.
我是为了你 伊莉西娅
I did it for you, Ilithyia.
为了你和你孩子的未来着想
To secure future for you and your child.
我希望我们能重归于好
I would mend rift between us.
弥补我当年犯下的愚蠢错误
One torn by my own foolish hands.
也许是我太愚蠢了
Perhaps it is I that have been foolish.
居然怀疑有诸神庇佑的
To ever doubt such dear friend
这么好的朋友
was blessed by the gods.
美酒和欢笑确实有效啊
Laughter and drink have done much
驱散了心头的乌云
to dispel darkening gloom.
很好
Good.
不过明天早上恐怕我要头痛欲裂了
But yet I fear shall see split head come morning.
你还满意吧
You stand satisfied then?
非常满意
In all things.
过去的都过去了 我们共同展望未来吧
Let us set past aside, and look towards deserving future.
这话说得太好了
Words of significant worth.
来吧 趁我们都还清醒 我们再去聊聊
Come, I would break more with you before sleep claims us.
我为先前的疑虑道歉
Apologies for earlier doubt.
今晚的宴会确实大有好处
This evening has proven most advantageous.
没错
Yes.
我都等不及明天的到来了
I long to see what dawn shall bring.
维苏威
Vesuvius.
多远
How far?
半天路程
Half a day's journey.
带上纳西尔
Take Nasir.
我尽可能拖住他们
I will hold them back for as long as I am able.
不
No.
我们并肩战斗
I stay by your side.
妮维雅
Naevia.